be a part or even be the center of our medical team? What if Musu could help us bring health care from clinics in cities to the doorsteps of her neighbors? Musu was 48 when I met her. And despite her amazing talent and grit, she hadn't had a paying job in 30 years. So what if technology could support her? What if we could invest in her with real training, equip her with real medicines, and have her have a real job? Well, in 2007, I was trying to answer these questions, and my wife and I were getting married that year. We asked our relatives to forgo the wedding registry gifts and instead donate some money so we could have some start-up money to launch a nonprofit. I promise you, I'm a lot more romantic than that. (Laughter) We ended up raising $6,000, teamed up with some Liberians and Americans and launched a nonprofit called Last Mile Health. Our goal is to bring a health worker within reach of everyone, everywhere. We designed a three-step process -- train, equip and pay -- to invest more deeply in volunteers like Musu to become paraprofessionals, to become community health workers. First we trained Musu to prevent, diagnose and treat the top 10 diseases afflicting families in her village. A nurse supervisor visited her every month to coach her. We equipped her with modern medical technology, like this $1 malaria rapid test, and put it in a backpack full of medicines like this to treat infections like pneumonia, and crucially, a smartphone, to help her track and report on epidemics. Last, we recognized the dignity in Musu's work. With the Liberian government, we created a contract, paid her and gave her the chance to have a real job. And she's amazing. Musu has learned over 30 medical skills, from screening children for malnutrition, to assessing the cause of a child's cough with a smartphone, to supporting people with HIV and providing follow-up care to patients who've lost their limbs. Working as part of our team, working as paraprofessionals, community health workers can help ensure that a lot of what your family doctor would do reaches the places that most family doctors could never go. One of my favorite things to do is to care for patients with community health workers. So last year I was visiting A.B., and like Musu, A.B. had had a chance to go to school. He was in middle school, in the eighth grade, when his parents died. He became an orphan and had to drop out. Last year, we hired and trained A.B. as a community health worker. And while he was making door to door house calls, he met this young boy named Prince, whose mother had had trouble breastfeeding him, and by the age of six months, Prince had started to waste away. A.B. had just been taught how to use this color-coded measuring tape that wraps around the upper arm of a child to diagnose malnutrition. A.B. noticed that Prince was in the red zone, which meant he had to be hospitalized. So A.B. took Prince and his mother to the river, got in a canoe and paddled for four hours to get to the hospital. Later, after Prince was discharged, A.B. taught mom how to feed baby a food supplement. A few months ago, A.B. took me to visit Prince, and he's a chubby little guy. (Laughter) He's meeting his milestones, he's pulled himself up to a stand, and is even starting to say a few words. I'm so inspired by these community health workers. I often ask them why they do what they do, and when I asked A.B., he said, "Doc, since I dropped out of school, this is the first time I'm having a chance to hold a pen to write. My brain is getting fresh." The stories of A.B. and Musu have taught me something fundamental about being human. Our will to serve others can actually help us transform our own conditions. I was so moved by how powerful the will to serve our neighbors can be a few years ago, when we faced a global catastrophe. In December 2013, something happened in the rainforests across the border from us in Guinea. A toddler named Emile fell sick with vomiting, fever and diarrhea. He lived in an area where the roads were sparse and there had been massive shortages of health workers. Emile died, and a few weeks later his sister died, and a few weeks later his mother died. And this disease would spread from one community to another. And it wasn't until three months later that the world recognized this as Ebola. When every minute counted, we had already lost months, and by then the virus had spread like wildfire all across West Africa, and eventually to other parts of the world. Businesses shut down, airlines started canceling routes. At the height of the crisis, when we were told that 1.4 million people could be infected, when we were told that most of them would die, when we had nearly lost all hope, I remember standing with a group of health workers in the rainforest where an outbreak had just happened. We were helping train and equip them to put on the masks, the gloves and the gowns that they needed to keep themselves safe from the virus while they were serving their patients. I remember the fear in their eyes. And I remember staying up at night, terrified if I'd made the right call to keep them in the field. When Ebola threatened to bring humanity to its knees, Liberia's community health workers didn't surrender to fear. They did what they had always done: they answered the call to serve their neighbors. Community members across Liberia learned the symptoms of Ebola, teamed up with nurses and doctors to go door-to-door to find the sick and get them into care. They tracked thousands of people who had been exposed to the virus and helped break the chain of transmission. Some ten thousand community health workers risked their own lives to help hunt down this virus and stop it in its tracks. (Applause) Today, Ebola has come under control in West Africa, and we've learned a few things. We've learned that blind spots in rural health care can lead to hot spots of disease, and that places all of us at greater risk. We've learned that the most efficient emergency system is actually an everyday system, and that system has to reach all communities, including rural communities like Emile's. And most of all, we've learned from the courage of Liberia's community health workers that we as people are not defined by the conditions we face, no matter how hopeless they seem. We're defined by how we respond to them. For the past 15 years, I've seen the power of this idea to transform everyday citizens into community health workers -- into everyday heroes. And I've seen it play out everywhere, from the forest communities of West Africa, to the rural fishing villages of Alaska. It's true, these community health workers aren't doing neurosurgery, but they're making it possible to bring health care within reach of everyone everywhere. So now what? Well, we know that there are still millions of people dying from preventable causes in rural communities around the world. And we know that the great majority of these deaths are happening in these 75 blue-shaded countries. What we also know is that if we trained an army of community health workers to learn even just 30 lifesaving skills, we could save the lives of nearly 30 million people by 2030. Thirty services could save 30 million lives by 2030. That's not just a blueprint -- we're proving this can be done. In Liberia, the Liberian government is training thousands of workers like A.B. and Musu after Ebola, to bring health care to every child and family in the country. And we've been honored to work with them, and are now teaming up with a number of organizations that are working across other countries to try to help them do the same thing. If we could help these countries scale, we could save millions of lives, and at the same time, we could create millions of jobs. We simply can't do that, though, without technology. People are worried that technology is going to steal our jobs, but when it comes to community health workers, technology has actually been vital for creating jobs. Without technology -- without this smartphone, without this rapid test -- it would have been impossible for us to be able to employ A.B. and Musu. And I think it's time for technology to help us train, to help us train people faster and better than ever before. As a doctor, I use technology to stay up-to-date and keep certified. I use smartphones, I use apps, I use online courses. But when A.B. wants to learn, he's got to jump back in that canoe and get to the training center. And when Musu shows up for training, her instructors are stuck using flip charts and markers. Why shouldn't they have the same access to learn as I do? If we truly want community health workers to master those lifesaving skills and even more, we've got to change this old-school model of education. Tech can truly be a game changer here. I've been in awe of the digital education revolution that the likes of Khan Academy and edX have been leading. And I've been thinking that it's time; it's time for a collision between the digital education revolution and the community health revolution. And so, this brings me to my TED Prize wish. I wish -- I wish that you would help us recruit the largest army of community health workers the world has ever known by creating the Community Health Academy, a global platform to train, connect and empower. (Applause) Thank you. Here's the idea: we'll create and curate the best in digital education resources. We will bring those to community health workers around the world, including A.B. and Musu. They'll get video lessons on giving kids vaccines and have online courses on spotting the next outbreak, so they're not stuck using flip charts. We'll help these countries accredit these workers, so that they're not stuck remaining an under-recognized, undervalued group, but become a renowned, empowered profession, just like nurses and doctors. And we'll create a network of companies and entrepreneurs who've created innovations that can save lives and help them connect to workers like Musu, so she can help better serve her community. And we'll work tirelessly to persuade governments to make community health workers a cornerstone of their health care plans. We plan to test and prototype the academy in Liberia and a few other partner countries, and then we plan to take it global, including to rural North America. With the power of this platform, we believe countries can be more persuaded that a health care revolution really is possible. My dream is that this academy will contribute to the training of hundreds of thousands of community members to help bring health care to their neighbors -- the hundreds of millions of them that live in the world's most remote communities, from the forest communities of West Africa, to the fishing villages of rural Alaska; from the hilltops of Appalachia, to the mountains of Afghanistan. If this vision is aligned with yours, head to communityhealthacademy.org, and join this revolution. Let us know if you or your organization or someone you know could help us as we try to build this academy over the next year. Now, as I look out into this room, I realize that our journeys are not self-made; they're shaped by others. And there have been so many here that have been part of this cause. We're so honored to be part of this community, and a community that's willing to take on a cause as audacious as this one, so I wanted to offer, as I end, a reflection. I think a lot more about what my father taught me. These days, I too have become a dad. I have two sons, and my wife and I just learned that she's pregnant with our third child. (Applause) Thank you. I was recently caring for a woman in Liberia who, like my wife, was in her third pregnancy. But unlike my wife, had had no prenatal care with her first two babies. She lived in an isolated community in the forest that had gone for 100 years without any health care until ... until last year when a nurse trained her neighbors to become community health workers. So here I was, seeing this patient who was in her second trimester, and I pulled out the ultrasound to check on the baby, and she started telling us stories about her first two kids, and I had the ultrasound probe on her belly, and she just stopped mid-sentence. She turned to me and she said, "Doc, what's that sound?" It was the first time she'd ever heard her baby's heartbeat. And her eyes lit up in the same way my wife's eyes and my own eyes lit up when we heard our baby's heartbeat. For all of human history, illness has been universal and access to care has not. But as a wise man once told me: no condition is permanent. It's time. It's time for us to go as far as it takes to change this condition together. Thank you. (Applause)
qui faisaient partie ou étaient au centre de notre équipe médicale ? Et si Musu pouvait nous aider à apporter les soins des cliniques des villes jusqu'au seuil de porte de ses voisins ? Musu avait 48 ans quand je l'ai rencontrée. Malgré son talent extraordinaire et son cran, elle n'avait pas eu de travail avec un salaire depuis 30 ans. Et si la technologie pouvait l'aider ? Et si nous investissions en elle avec une vraie formation, l'équipions de vrais médicaments et qu'elle avait un vrai travail ? En 2007, j'essayais de répondre à ces questions et comme ma femme et moi nous mariions cette année-là, nous avons demandé à notre famille de laisser tomber les cadeaux de mariage et de nous donner de l'argent pour que nous puissions démarrer une organisation à but non lucratif. Je vous promets, je suis bien plus romantique que ça. (Rires) Nous avons recueilli 6 000 $, fait équipe avec des Libériens et Américains et lancé « La dernière ligne droite de la santé ». Notre objectif est que tout le monde ait un agent de santé accessible, partout. Nous avons un processus en trois étapes -- former, équiper et payer -- pour investir plus profondément dans les volontaires comme Musu pour qu'ils deviennent des paraprofessionnels, des agents de santé communautaires. Nous avons formé Musu à éviter, diagnostiquer et traiter les 10 maladies majeures affectant les familles dans son village. Un infirmier superviseur allait la voir tous les mois pour l'encadrer. Nous l'avons équipée de technologie médicale moderne, comme ce test rapide pour la malaria qui coûte un dollar, et lui avons donné un sac-à-dos plein de médicaments pour traiter des infections comme la pneumonie, et, c'est crucial, un smartphone pour qu'elle surveille et signale les épidémies. Pour finir, nous avons reconnu la dignité du travail de Musu. Avec le gouvernement libérien, nous avons créé un contrat, l'avons payée et lui avons donné un vrai travail. Elle est géniale. Musu a appris plus de 30 compétences médicales, du dépistage de la malnutrition chez les enfants à l'évaluation de la cause de la toux d'un enfant avec un smartphone en passant par le soutien des personnes atteintes de VIH et le suivi des patients ayant perdu leurs membres. Travailler dans notre équipe, en tant que paraprofessionnels, les agents de santé communautaires peuvent garantir que ce que fait un médecin de famille arrive jusqu'aux endroits où la plupart des médecins de famille n'iront pas. Une des choses que j'adore faire, c'est prendre soin des patients avec les agents de santé. L'année dernière, j'ai été voir A.B. et, comme Musu, A.B. avait eu la chance d'aller à l'école. Il était au collège, en 4ème, quand ses parents sont morts. Il est devenu orphelin et a dû abandonner l'école. L'année dernière, nous avons engagé et formé A.B. comme agent de santé. Alors qu'il allait de maison en maison voir ses patients, il a rencontré ce jeune garçon, Prince, dont la mère avait des difficultés pour le nourrir au sein et, à l'âge de six mois, Prince avait commencé à perdre du poids. A.B. venait d'apprendre à utiliser ce ruban de mesure coloré qui entoure le haut du bras d'un enfant pour diagnostiquer la malnutrition. A.B. a remarqué que Prince était dans la zone rouge, il devait être hospitalisé. Alors A.B. a emmené Prince et sa mère à la rivière, est monté dans un canoë et a pagayé pendant quatre heures pour aller à l'hôpital. Après que Prince est sorti de l'hôpital, A.B. a appris à la mère à donner des compléments alimentaires au bébé. Quelques mois après, A.B. m'a emmené voir Prince et c'est un petit gars joufflu. (Rires) Il progresse, arrive à se mettre debout et commence même à dire quelques mots. Je suis inspiré par ces agents de santé communautaires. Je leur demande souvent pourquoi ils font cela et quand j'ai demandé à A.B., il a dit : « Doc, depuis que j'ai quitté l'école, c'est la première fois que j'ai l'opportunité de tenir un crayon pour écrire. Mon cerveau se rafraîchit. » Les histoires d'A.B. et de Musu m'ont appris quelque chose de fondamental sur le fait d'être humain. Notre volonté d'aider les autres peut nous aider à transformer notre propre situation. J'ai été si ému par la force de notre volonté à aider les autres il y a quelques années, face à une catastrophe mondiale. En décembre 2013, il s'est produit quelque chose dans la forêt tropicale en Guinée. Un bambin, Émile, est tombé malade, il vomissait, avait de la fièvre et la diarrhée. Il vivait dans une région où les routes sont rares et il a un fort manque d'agents de santé. Émile est mort et, quelques semaines après, sa sœur est morte et puis sa mère. Cette maladie allait se propager d'une communauté à l'autre. Ce n'est que trois mois plus tard que le monde a reconnu cela comme étant Ebola. Quand chaque minute comptait, nous avions perdu des mois et le virus s'était déjà propagé tel un feu de forêt en Afrique de l'Ouest puis dans d'autres parties du monde. Les entreprises fermaient, les compagnies aériennes annulaient des vols. A l'apogée de la crise, quand on nous a dit que 1,4 million de personnes pourraient être atteintes, que la plupart allaient mourir, quand nous avions perdu presque tout espoir, je me suis souvenu m'être tenu avec des agents de santé dans la forêt tropicale où une épidémie s'était déclenchée. Nous aidions à les former et équiper pour qu'ils mettent le masque, les gants et la blouse nécessaires pour se protéger du virus alors qu'ils servaient leurs patients. Je me souviens de la peur dans leurs yeux. Je me souviens ne pas avoir dormi, terrifié quant à mon choix de les laisser sur le terrain. Quand Ebola a menacé de mettre l'humanité à genoux, les agents de santé libériens n'ont pas cédé face à la peur. Ils ont fait comme toujours : ils ont répondu à l'appel pour aider leurs voisins. Les membres des communautés du Liberia ont appris les symptômes d'Ebola, ont fait équipe avec des infirmiers et médecins pour faire du porte à porte et soigner les malades. Ils ont repéré des milliers de personnes qui avaient été exposées au virus et ont aidé à briser la chaîne de transmission. Dix mille agents de santé communautaires ont risqué leur propre vie pour aider à traquer ce virus et à empêcher qu'il se propage. (Applaudissements) Aujourd'hui, Ebola est sous contrôle en Afrique de l'Ouest et nous avons appris des choses. Les angles morts dans les soins ruraux peuvent être des points chauds de maladie et cela nous met tous en grand danger. Le système de secours le plus efficace est un système quotidien et que ce système doit atteindre toutes les communautés, y compris les communautés rurales comme celle d’Émile. Et surtout, nous avons appris du courage des agents de santé libériens que nous, en tant que personnes, ne sommes pas définis par notre situation, même si elle semble désespérée. Nous sommes définis par notre réponse à la situation. Ces 15 dernières années, j'ai vu le pouvoir de cette idée transformer des citoyens ordinaires en agents de santé communautaires -- en héros du quotidien. J'ai vu cela à l’œuvre partout des communautés forestières de l'Afrique de l'Ouest aux villages de pêcheurs en Alaska. C'est vrai, ces agents de santé communautaires ne font pas de neurochirurgie, mais ils rendent cela possible d'avoir des soins de santé accessibles à tous partout. Et maintenant ? Nous savons qu'il y a encore des millions de gens qui meurent de causes évitables dans les communautés rurales du monde. Nous savons que la grande majorité de ces morts se produisent dans ces 75 pays en bleu. Nous savons aussi que si nous formions une armée d'agents de santé communautaires et leur apprenions ne serait-ce que 30 compétences vitales, nous pourrions sauver les vies de près de 30 millions de personnes d'ici à 2030. Trente services sauveraient 30 millions de vie d'ici à 2030. Ce n'est pas qu'un plan -- nous prouvons que cela peut être fait. Au Liberia, le gouvernement libérien forme des milliers d'agents comme A.B. et Musu après Ebola, pour apporter des soins à tous les enfants et toutes les familles du pays. Nous avons eu l'honneur de travailler avec eux et faisons équipe avec beaucoup d'organisations qui travaillent dans d'autres pays pour aider à faire la même chose. Si nous pouvions aider ces pays à étendre ce projet, nous sauverions des millions de vies et, en même temps, créerions des millions d'emplois. Néanmoins, nous ne pouvons pas le faire sans la technologie. Les gens ont peur que la technologie ne vole nos emplois mais quand il s'agit des agents de santé, la technologie est vitale à la création d'emplois. Sans technologie -- sans ce smartphone, sans un test rapide -- il nous aurait été impossible d'employer A.B. et Musu. Il est temps que la technologie nous aide à former, nous aide à former les gens plus vite et mieux que jamais auparavant. En tant que médecin, j'utilise la technologie pour rester à jour. J'utilise des smartphones, applications et cours en ligne. Quand A.B. veut apprendre, il doit retourner dans ce canoë et aller au centre de formation. Quand Musu vient se former, ses instructeurs doivent utiliser du papier et des marqueurs. Pourquoi ne devraient-ils pas avoir le même accès à l'apprentissage que moi ? Si nous voulons que les agents de santé maîtrisent ces compétences vitales et plus encore, nous devons changer ce vieux modèle éducatif. La technologie peut changer les choses. Je suis émerveillé par la révolution éducative numérique que Khan Academy, edX et les autres ont menée. Je pense qu'il est temps qu'il y ait une collision entre la révolution éducative numérique et la révolution de la communauté de santé. Cela m'amène à mon vœu pour mon TED Prize. Je souhaiterais -- Je souhaiterais que vous nous aidiez à recruter la plus grande armée d'agents de santé communautaires qui ait jamais existé en créant l'Académie de Santé Communautaire, une plateforme mondiale pour former, connecter et autonomiser. (Applaudissements) Merci. Voici l'idée : nous allons créer et organiser les meilleures ressources en éducation numérique. Nous les amènerons aux agents de santé communautaires à travers le monde, y compris A.B. et Musu. Ils auront des leçons vidéos pour vacciner des enfants et des cours en ligne pour repérer la prochaine épidémie, plus besoin de papier. Nous aiderons ces pays à accréditer ces agents afin qu'ils ne restent pas un groupe qui manque de reconnaissance, sous-évalué mais que cela devienne une profession renommée, habilitée comme les infirmiers et les médecins. Nous créerons un réseau d'entreprises et d'entrepreneurs ayant créé des innovations pouvant sauver des vies et les mettrons en contact avec des agents comme Musu pour qu'elle puisse mieux servir sa communauté. Nous travaillerons sans relâche pour persuader les gouvernements de faire des agents de santé communautaires une pierre angulaire de leur plan de santé. Nous prévoyons de tester et faire un prototype de l'académie au Liberia et dans quelques autres pays partenaires puis de la rendre mondiale, qu'elle existe même en Amérique du Nord. Avec le pouvoir de cette plateforme, nous croyons que les pays peuvent être persuadés que la révolution de santé est vraiment possible. Mon rêve est que cette académie contribue à former des centaines de milliers de membres communautaires pour apporter des soins de santé à leurs voisins -- les centaines de millions qui vivent dans les communautés les plus reculées, des communautés forestières d'Afrique de l'Ouest aux villages de pêcheurs de l'Alaska ; des sommets des Appalaches aux montagnes afghanes. Si vous êtes d'accord avec cette vision, allez sur communityhealthacademy.org et rejoignez la révolution. Faites-nous savoir si votre organisation, une de vos connaissances peut nous aider alors que nous essayons de créer cette académie durant l'année. En regardant dans cette pièce, je réalise que nos voyages ne sont pas créés seuls ; ils sont façonnés par les autres. Il y a tellement de gens ici qui ont fait partie de cette cause. Je suis honoré de faire partie de cette communauté, une communauté qui est prête à s'attaquer à une cause aussi audacieuse que celle-là alors, pour finir, je voulais offrir une réflexion. Je pense beaucoup à ce que mon père m'a appris. Ces jours-ci, je suis devenu père. J'ai deux fils et ma femme et moi venons d'apprendre qu'elle est enceinte de notre 3ème enfant. (Applaudissements) Merci. J'ai récemment pris soin d'une femme au Liberia qui, comme ma femme, en était à sa troisième grossesse. Mais, contrairement à ma femme, elle n'a eu aucun soin prénatal avec ses deux premiers bébés. Elle vivait, dans la forêt, dans une communauté isolée qui avait passé 100 ans sans aucun soin de santé jusqu'à... jusqu'à l'année dernière quand une infirmière a formé ses voisins pour qu'ils soient agents de santé. Me voilà à voir cette patiente qui en était à son second trimestre et j'ai sorti l'échographe pour vérifier si le bébé allait bien. Elle nous a raconté des histoires sur ses deux premiers enfants, j'ai mis la sonde à ultrasons sur son ventre et elle s'est arrêtée en pleine phrase. Elle m'a regardé et a dit : « Doc, c'est quoi ce son ? » C'était la première fois qu'elle entendait battre le cœur de son bébé. Ses yeux se sont éclairés de la même façon que ceux de ma femme et les miens quand nous entendons battre le cœur de notre bébé. Durant toute l'histoire de l'humanité, les maladies ont été universelles, mais pas l'accès aux soins. Mais comme un homme sage m'a dit un jour : aucune situation n'est permanente. Il est temps. Il est temps d'aller aussi loin que nécessaire pour changer cette situation ensemble. Merci. (Applaudissements)